[Music] what is root well for for me it's
always important to emphasize that it's a it's
an open-source project by the high energy physics
community for the community here uh the developers
are right at CERN or at our partner institute and
um we are engaging with our user community on a
daily basis So um if you have any questions about
root and how to use it in particular for your pro
problem we also have a forum where you can ask
your questions So it's um it's really it's really
a a community effort and um at some point who
knows maybe you might contribute yourself Root
was mainly developed really to drive the analysis
at the LHC So that was started in the 90s when the
LHC was really planned I think also root started
around that time maybe late 90s And uh of course
the example that we're most proud of that we
show every time is uh um the analysis that led
to the Hicks discovery in 2012 they were already
done using root So for the root was used for the
plotting um the statistical analysis and of course
also for storing the data and and processing the
data So I think this is quite familiar to you
maybe I who has seen this plot already Okay Yeah
already a few So I think then after your summer
student lectures everyone will know it This is the
um the measurement of hick boson decay decaying
into two photons and by the CMS experiment And
here you have um the measurement of the hicks mass
and and signal strength in both dioton and for
leptton channels by atlas So um yeah I mentioned
that there are several things that root can do
like plotting histograms here on this slide I
just give you an overview of um what it can do So
not everything is relevant for today Today we will
mostly focus really on the basics that you need to
get started doing some analysis in with root right
So let's say your supervisor gives you a root file
with some end to so some data set that he wants
you to analyze by the end of today the goal is
that you are able to do this with the cutting edge
classes of root But in case you wonder what root
can do besides um like the final analysis steps
here's the the overview And um some things we
are proud of in particular is uh for example
the C++ inter interpreter is quite powerful
So root started as um um is actually not a Python
library So it's a C++ library All of these parts
of root are implemented in C++ for performance
reasons And um all of this C++ interpretation
layer that allows us to also use it from Python
is quite um quite impressive Then um we have
besides functions for data storing and analysis
and plotting we also have some advanced libraries
for statistical analysis is roofit You might have
heard about it if you are already working with
these uh collaborations or for machine learning
we have TMVA and um then our newest uh product
so to speak is our data frame that we use then for
declaring your analysis and running it efficiently
and um so I was mentioning there's a lot of data
stored in root files Yeah So root is is used to
store data like the one the data that was recorded
by the experiments to discover the hick boson And
actually the impressive thing about roots data
storage system is that you can dump arbitrary
C++ classes in a root file and store whatever you
want like this And the experiments at the LHC they
they use this to really store the output of their
detectors at every stage of the analysis pipeline
So they have their own custom classes to represent
hits in the detector Then they save it into some
raw format That's how they usually call it
in jargon Then after they reconstruct their
particles that the detector measures they save
like a list of um of laptons jets etc again back
in a in a new root file And then so there are
between one and n further reduction steps But
at some point um you have reduced then your data
to some digestible format that you can also store
on your laptop and then do analysis with this Yeah
So we will come um um to back the to we will come
back to this again later when talking about our
data frame because our data frame and everything
else that we show today is really targeted
towards this um uh final step of the analysis
where you have your uh root files with some
tabular data and then you make plots out of it
Today we will talk really about these uh final
end user data analysis starting with histogramming
fitting So fitting is a bit of a jargon for
a parameter estimation in high energy physics
meaning we want to find we have some hypothesis
that depends on on parameters and we want to
figure out what are the ones that might match
the data best Then we talk about how you read
data from from root files and then how you do a
more complicated analysis with our data frame and
uh let's go to the Jupyter notebooks [Music] Now
let's uh let's get started with by looking at
histograms So histograms is a very uh a histogram
is a very powerful tool to reduce data right so
that's why we use it in high energy physics
all the time when you have measured millions
of events you don't always care about um all the
individual measurements you want to aggregate them
in in in some bins you know you want to know how
much measurements were between in this case here
for example 80 and 84 4 GV or something and um
so you you just need some counts in the different
ranges or called bins also called bins and then do
some um statistic analysis with these bin counts
So um and actually this example of a histogram
here is again from this hick discovery analysis
this time uh from no it's not the hick discovery
analysis it's later yeah you see this here square
root of s3 TV so this is from the LHC uh run two
but nevertheless same kind of analysis so the
hicks decaying into four laptops and um all the
histogram programs in root are represented by a
C++ class or to you it looks like a Python class
when you are using root from Python and the name
of these classes always starts with a t that's
that's our convention in root then you have h for
histogram then you have the number of dimensions
in the histogram so here one and then you have a
data type uh for the for the axis of the histogram
So in this case it's a one-dimensional histogram
where the access type is of type double So um like
a real number right represented by a computer And
um another example would be TH2I So two
dimensional histogram uh for integer
observables So um now we actually run some code
So let's see how you would create a histogram in
root and fill it with some toy data So first you
need to import root Is it maybe I can zoom in a
little bit Can everyone read it also in the back
is it large enough okay Nice Thanks So uh let's
let's import root and create our first histogram
So I will go uh through this constructor call
here um a little bit in in detail but then
afterwards the pattern is always the same Yeah
Many root objects uh in their constructor they
accept first the name of the object that should
be unique because root is using this internally to
um identify the object Then you have a title
that is used mostly for visualization And uh
then for the histogram you need to give the number
of bins and the range So and then the final step
here is we are sampling 5,000 random values from
a gshian distribution and fill the histogram with
it So that takes some time because it's 5,000 data
points not just uh it's actually the the um the
import that takes some time in the beginning but
then creating the histogram is rather fast and
uh if you want to know more about how to use the
TH1 object you can go to our reference guide but
usually you can also reach the same page by just
googling TH1 uh root or sometimes it helps to say
CERN root because root is quite ambiguous So if
you Google th1 str root you would probably land on
the same page So um how do you draw a histogram
right now we didn't see anything It's just an
object that lives in on the computer but we can't
really see it So um to draw anything we are using
here this um JavaScript root back end So this is
a um an implementation of um of root plotting in
JavaScript So that means it runs natively on the
browser and then you can also interact with your
plots So this is what we recommend you to use
when you are plotting your root histograms in
the browser from a Jupyter notebook you enable
our JavaScript plotting back end with this
um magic command JS root and then set it to on
and uh and drawing always follows the same pattern
First you create a canvas uh that you draw on So
this is of type t canvas and um then you draw the
object on the canvas with this object.draw method
In this case it's the histogram.draw draw and then
finally you draw the canvas and that's it So this
will always be the same thing also later on for
um for graphs or other objects in root So let's
do it and then you have a nice visualization of
the histogram where you can also zoom Um you
can reset the axis by double clicking on the
surface and you can also hover with the mouse
over uh over the histogram and read how many
counts are there Quite useful if your supervisor
is looking over your shoulder and asking so how
many bins how many counts are there again in
this bin So this is I mean uh it seems like a
simple feature but it's quite useful to quickly
know how many counts you have in a given bin
um root functions So um I already mentioned it
before So we often compare hypothesis with data
in histograms and the hypothesis we also want to
represented in sort kind of probability density
function for example So we need a way to represent
functions as well in in the root world and
um we do this with yet another class So this
time it's called TF for T function and then
you have the number of dimensions right after So
um you don't need a data type because a function
is just a mathematical relation It doesn't store
any data itself So it's just TF then the number of
dimension So uh as an example let us now create
a two-dimensional function that represents this
sin x^2 minus y^ 2 function So um again you give
a name you give a title and then instead of number
of bins you where you don't need that it's a
function is not bins you just give the limits
for the for the axis that are required So two
dimensional function has two axis x and y and
then to draw it you follow the same pattern
again So you create a new canvas you draw the
uh object on the canvas and you can also pass some
uh drawing options in the string You will find
um all the options in the the reference guide
Here we are using this surf one object sorry
um option to draw a surface plot in like the style
number one I think if you use surface two it will
look different So um in this case we get here
this surface plot that we can again interact with
because it's JavaScript root So uh you can really
look at this function from all angles Actually I'm
curious now how how surface two would look like
It's a slightly different way of representing the
surface apparently Nice Okay So um how do we now
bring the functions and the histograms together
in a likelihood fit or um or a kai square fit well
um let's try to fit our histogram from before the
one with a with a gosh and random numbers Um so
for this we need to create a new one-dimensional
function a TF1 And uh now this is really the most
complicated part of this presentation So so bear
with me here I use a slightly more advanced um
uh feature in root to define this TF1 object So
what I want to do now is um I want to define the
function in C++ Let's say you have a complicated
fitting function that you don't want to define in
Python but in C++ for performance reasons Then you
can um actually write C++ in a Jupyter notebook
with root by just prefixing the sale using this
percent CPP magic at the beginning of the cell
So all the content of the cell thereafter is
then sent to root's internal C++ interpreter
and then you have uh this function available
in the root module as if it would have been
part of root itself So this quite powerful and
uh it really allows you to to benefit from the
upsides of both C++ and Python in one script So
um yeah I really like to show this and here we are
defining this gshian function here that depends on
uh some observables x So you can think of
this as the observable on the x-axis of the
histogram It's only one dimensional So we are
only um getting the zero element of this array
and then this gshion is also depending on some
parameters in this uh array par And here we have
uh two parameters One overall scaling constant
here R0 and then the mean R1 And you see that this
gshion here is always has a standard deviation
of one So it's a bit of a simplified version
of the gshion So just a gshion with the floating
mean and and normalization So we define this Now
in the definition of the parameters I see that you
are indexing par and x as if there were arrays but
then in the in the typing you uh it says only
double as if it's not an array So I'm a little
bit confused Do we see this star here maybe so
this is um how you declare arrays in C actually So
um yes it if it would be just double x that
would mean this function accepts a double but
um but if you have this double star x it
means it accepts an array of double of
um so the length is not clear but um it's
just a basically a pointer to the a place
in memory where this array starts and this
is how you are um passing around arrays in
in C++ as well So it's like a something
that the language inherited from from
C and um now we can use it as if it would be part
of the root module So we use it thish in this case
to instantiate this TF1 function object Um because
what I've shown you before with the TF2 example
was we are giving the mathematical expression for
the function as a string Let's throw in the second
constructor argument Um this time we're passing
it passing the a C++ function that is basically
wrapped by this root function object So let's do
this And we get our own C++ function here from
the root module So everything that we declared to
the root interpreter with this percent CP magic
you can then get it from the uh from root like
that So we have now defined this fit function and
um to do the fit all that you need to do is you
need to call t th1 so the histogram fit So here
the th1 is our is called h that was the one from
the beginning and then we call the fit method on
it and you pass the fit function that should be a
th1 object sorry a tf1 object in that case and um
and then you can also give some options to the fit
just like in the in the case of drawing So there
you pass some drawing object uh drawing options
Here you're passing fitting options We only use
one We are using this S option here So that the
fit um function actually returns an object with
a fit result So S stands for save in this case
Actually it means save the result of the of the
fit in this returned value here Rest for result So
it does that and it also prints you the fit result
on the screen actual parameter values You see them
here in the very bottom So P 0 and P1 um or P1
This was the mean right we sampled the the random
values from a gshian distribution with mean zero
So if the fit value is more or less compatible
with zero that makes sense So it is this is
the case So it's almost zero within one standard
deviation So that's that's okay And then the and
then the normalization constant well it's um it's
not exactly the number of events in the toy data
set because uh in the definition of the gshion we
didn't really care about the the about normalizing
the PDF or any bin width or whatever So that
means this con constant here is a bit bit random
But um it is um uh you can see it here it's 500
And then you have some other information like
how many um iterations did the minimizer need to
find the minimum How far does it estimate it is
away from the minimum This is this EDM estimated
distance from the minimum That's a bit technical
but what you maybe know from the from your physics
classes is this um kaiquare quantity So you see it
here again in the fit results and when you draw
now the histogram after doing this fit So again
the same way create canvas draw the histogram um
draw the canvas you see that the um fit function
is included in the visualization And when you now
hover with the mouse over the histogram you will
see not only the bin counts but also the value of
the function So you can really compare things by
eye which is sometimes quite useful You don't
you don't always want to rely on kiquare test
statistics or something Sometimes this can deceive
you It's always good to compare things by eye
Remember it was a bit of a bit of a complicated
way in which we were defining this gshian function
Right we were creating our own C++ function
to define the this gshian TF1 but I mean since
gshian distribution is so common in data analysis
there's also builtin function in root it's called
gaus and then you can just fit your histogram to
this built-in function which is by the way this
uh the same function that we use to to fill the
random numbers So um you can think of it uh like
there are some TF1 objects that always live in in
the root module no matter if you created them or
not and you can reference them by um using these
uh names in a string So for the full list of the
supported built-in functions you can follow this
link but here we're using the gshion and we get
the same result as before at least for um for
the mean for the constant we now get something
else because it's um the normalization is is
a bit different in the in the built-in gshion
and then we also have now an estimate for the
standard deviation which is compatible with one
So that that matches again the um the gshion with
mean zero and standard deviation one that we used
to fill the the histogram with So we now draw
the histogram You see here the same result as
before because now we just use the built-in gshion
instead of our custom one But of course the end
result is the same uh once your fit becomes more
complicated like in the case of these LHC hick
combination analysis yeah then you don't only
fit one histogram at a time then you start to
fit like 50 or even 100 histograms because then
each analysis group they measure their own decay
channel or their own observable and then you want
to do some combined measurement where you are then
um uh fitting all these histograms with a common
hypothesis that has like a a global hypothesis
on the on the hick mass for example So you start
to have a very large likelihood function and to
actually find the minimum you need to take care
that this likelihood function is implemented in
a very efficient way so that the minimizer can
evaluate it very very often And um we have a
library inside root that you can use to implement
these very efficient probability density functions
and likelihoods It's called RFIT you will maybe
use it when you are working with CMS or Atlas or
any of the big LHC experiments in in your time
as a summer student Okay we can also visualize
graphs in root not surprisingly and this is quite
a common thing to do So just a set of points on
the x and y axis and the class that allows
you to do that is is called the tg graph and
um I just give you one example how to use it
so that you have it seen have seen it at least
once but it's it's quite intuitive right so um
in this case the tragraph doesn't even take a
name or a title as a constructor argument um in
this case we are just fitting the t graph with a
set of points from a parabola So here we have um
so in a in this loop between 20 and minus 20 and
21 So actually that means from minus 20 to 20
inclusive we are filling the points the graph
with x and minus x^2 And then to draw the um the
graph you can do the same thing In this example
we're actually using some member functions of the
graph to define the style So here the marker style
the the color of the line when you draw it and
and the title It looks like this in the end It's
uh not uh not not very surprising So you see here
these um um points on the parabola that we were
filling the graph with And um again since it's
JavaScript root you can hover over the points
and see their x and y values So just to show
you an example for different drawing options
So here is another one If you draw a graph on a
canvas with this tgraphd draw you can also say hey
um draw it in this uh bar plot style So that's
what the B stands for The A stands for redraw the
axis Well this is by the way I think the default
behavior anyway And then um and then the B stands
for bar plot and again one is just the first kind
of bar plot style that root has built in And then
you have a bar plot instead of a regular u um
plot scatter plot with points connected by a line
So um these were some basic plotting examples
but what I really like to show you now is some uh
examples for plots of plots that are very common
in high energy physics and sometimes difficult to
implement with other tools Yeah like um here we
see here this uh histogram stack for example you
have here um some points with the observed data
here in black but what the hicks analysis here
in the for leptton channel did is they didn't
compare the data to some um to some function
like we did with our TF1 toy analysis but you were
actually comparing the data to a simulation so to
simulate ated data that is then also represented
in a histogram And uh to visual visually disting
distinguish them we are often representing the
actual data in these um black dots with arrow bars
and then the predictions So the simulated data for
a given hickmass hypothesis in this example we are
um representing this in the shaded areas So these
are also histograms Yeah TH1s the blue one here
for this um dibbon background and the red one
for the hick boson signal So these are then also
histograms filled with Monte Carlo predictions and
you see that you have different um components of
this Monte Carlo predictions So you have this um
uh the signal component here in red the background
dioon background in blue and then some other
backgrounds in in purple And you want to stack
these on top of each other in your in your canvas
to represent the full expectation um in your for
this measurement We have a class in roof It's
called the TH stack and um you create a TH
stack from a list of histograms and then when you
draw the histogram stack so if you call TH stack
drawdraw it will um give you something that looks
very similar already to this kind of plots that I
showed you in the beginning with the data to Monte
Carlo comparisons So what we are doing here is
um we are creating an array of actually three
TH1Ds Yeah one-dimensional histograms Then uh
okay we set some title here for and we create this
TH stack object here and then in a loop we are
um filling these individual histograms with random
numbers So in between these random number filling
I'm changing the the mean of the of the gshion of
this function that I sample from just so that the
three histograms are not the same right and then
um also the color is is different for the three
histograms and then um the histogram is added to
this stack and in the end we draw the stack and
that's what you see then here in in the output of
the cell and when you hover over the uh bins Again
you see actually the bin counts for each histogram
in the stack as if you would have drawn them
individually So another example for for a high
energy physics specific use case is here uh these
efficiency curves So um this is maybe requires
some explanation So what do we mean by efficiency
curve so often you have uh an analysis where you
are doing some filtering So let's say you have um
um a mass spectrum of a of um of some um yeah four
leptton resonance like we use in the in the six
analysis that I just showed And you want to filter
some your your events according to some criteria
like um events that that only have well identified
lepttons or some or events with a certain
um um mass range So then um you want to see okay
how many events are in my histogram before and
after the filter so that you can compare okay
how much of the signal survived the filters how
much of the background is still left to do these
kind of studies So um yeah filtering is very very
much essential for high energy physics u analysis
and by filter efficiency I just mean the rate of
events that survive the filter So often when you
do an analysis you want to find filters where 100%
of the signal events survive and fortunately 0%
background events but that's uh usually never the
case So you have to make a compromise and for this
reason it's important to study these filtering
efficiencies Um so I show you here an example
on on how you could do that Let's say you have
uh two histograms One events one histogram with
um um uh with the events before the filtering and
one right after So this age pass for the passing
events and then total for the the total events
before the filtering So in in this example I
I just set up random gshion data sets again So
um let me just plot them It's easier to talk
about it then So here I I uh for both the passing
histogram in red and the total histogram in blue
I just sample them from a gshian distribution
So but let's pretend this is really uh you got to
do this histogram by doing some proper uh analysis
of of a selection right and um then you want to
know what are the filtering efficiencies in each
bin So for each bin um how much events of the blue
histogram are still left in the red one Um and
uh this is quite easy in general because it's
just you need to divide the one histogram over the
other and then you have the the ratio But um the
problem is when your professor then then comes and
asks you hey you told me what uh this efficiency
ratio here but I have no idea what the uncertainty
is and please add the error bars to your
efficiency plot Then um okay so what do you do you
think about your gshian error propagation that you
did in the physics lab and and then you realize
that you might get the wrong results with this
because inefficiency is by definition between zero
and one and if you do go gshian error propagation
then um this is not considered So you might have
error bars in the end that extend above one or
below zero So your professor comes back to you and
and tells you hey I don't trust in your results it
looks uh looks unphysical So then um you actually
have to do some Beijian error estimation where you
consider like in a prior that your efficiency is
between zero and one and that's quite complicated
and this T efficiency class takes care of it for
you That's really the message here so that
you don't need to uh do this complicated
error propagation yourself So um that's why
if you then create this t efficiency here with
um from the passing and failing histogram and
then draw it then you will see it automatically
comes with the arrow bars that are using this
correct um uncertainty estimation for efficiencies
[Music] This exercise is very sim similar
to what I showed you in the presentation
So you're defining a model function in
C++ and um and fit it to a histogram
The difference is that the histogram is not filled
with random numbers but this time it's filled from
a from a a Python list And the function is not a
a simple C++ function with only one function body
but it's actually um a function that calls two
other functions So we have here one for the for
the background one for for the signal peak They
are defined individually just before And then you
get this total fit function here And um so in
the end once you fit the function to the data
with the similar commands to what we saw before
in the lecture it should look like this So that's
the exa expected results of the the exercise You
have some details detail instructions here and um
the solution is also at the bottom I encourage you
not to look at it until you have really done this
yourself Uh let's look at the solution together
very quickly So um so for the fit function it's
like in this example with the custom gshion from
the from the lecture So you pass here the the C++
function via the root module Then you give the
minimum of X and Y sorry of just of X and the
number of parameters which is is four So this
is probably the most complicated part because
you need to infer the number of parameters from
reading here the function definitions So here you
know that um so here the background it uses part
zero one and two So that one has three already the
peak uses par zero and uh and that's it So that
means three plus one in total four parameter and
um and this information needs to be known by the
by the TF1 object so that it can internally create
the the arrays of parameters with the right size
Okay So then and then you fit um and then you fit
here the the the function to the histogram here
There's also a little gotcha that tripped me off
at some point Yeah So you get here this um error
message but it tells you what to do right so you
can um use this save option So that's um this
warning doesn't happen And then um for drawing
the new information that you needed was here
this E option So um capital E is the drawing
option for drawing histogram with arrow bars So
you might either find this in the documentation
for drawing histograms or just if you Google CERN
root how to draw arrow bars it will probably show
you Oh and that's a general advice ROOT is not
the most googleable name for a software framework
because root might also mean other things with
computers the super user or just the tree Um so
if you Google for something ROOT related it's
good to ask for CERN root So that's the advice
[Music] 2. ROOT File
The root files are really what's at the core
of of doing an analysis because this is where
you read the data from and potentially also where
you read your data or the results of your analysis
uh back to be able to reuse or to reinpret. The
cool thing about these root files is really that
you can write any object uh to the files Um so
the the a root file we refer to it as a TFile,
so again the `T` at the beginning;
and that's really the the kind of the
object that you use to interact with when you're
running ROOT or when you're doing your analysis in
a in a notebook Um so the files they're kind of
special It's it's not like you can open them in
a text editor and see what's in there. They're
are binary files, and the reason behind this
is that we can apply compression and all kinds of
trickery to make sure that the files are as small
and as optimal as it needed to be, because well as
you saw we have 2 exabyte of data So we kind of have
to think about uh how we store these. You cannot
just write them down. We talk about ROOT files but
really what's inside of them is uh kind of like
a hierarchy and um if you use your terminal and
you print for example what's in a directory you
see that there are maybe subdirectories and files
ROOT files kind of have the same feeling where you
can have directories inside the root files or um
or objects um that are yeah kind of hierarchical
how to use and how to interact with a root file
Um let's start with just importing ROOT as usual
Uh this is always how we start Um let's wait for
it to finish importing There we are And now the
T file So in this situation we want to create a
T file from scratch So we don't have any data yet
but we want to write some results to to a new file
or um well see how it works So to create a T file
um kind of similar to what you saw with uh TF1 and
uh and all kinds of of uh root functions really
you just create a file by calling root t file
and it takes two two arguments The first one
is actually the name of your file Um and the
extension we use is root So anytime you find a
file that has root you know or you can be fairly
certain that it's a root file And then the second
parameter is kind of the mode or the option you
give to to the T file um constructor and it kind
of basically tells uh root or the T file creator
what you want to do with the file and it kind of
describes the policies on how you want to handle
the file So in this case I I said recreate which
means that I tell root that okay even if the file
already exists uh I don't care what's in it just
remove everything and let me start from scratch
This is can be a bit of a dangerous uh option
So if you only want to read what I recommend
or what we recommend is to not give any option
then it will always use the default read option
uh which means it's read only So you cannot
modify it Uh so yeah when you're handling data
uh that would be the recommended way of doing
it And then if you're done with the with with
your file if you're done writing it or reading
it or whatever you want to do with it you want
to close it So you can close it again uh by
calling f close Good to note here is that in
case your program terminates or if the the the
object we call f is destroyed the file is closed
automatically So in most cases you don't have to
um actively do this Another nice thing especially
because now we're using Python I don't know who
has ever opened a file in Python using the width
then you have like the file name whatever Yeah I
see a couple of hands Good Uh we can do exactly
the same thing here So we have with root t file
and then exactly the same constructor as my my
file You can do something with the file inside
the scope and then you will see that once you
exit the scope the file gets properly closed
and you don't need to worry about it Suppose
we want to get the size of the file We can
say my file dot or actually want to print
it file dot size and we can see that the file
currently has 220 bytes already u which is the
metadata that gets created when you create a t
file Um but there's no content yet Okay Um the
content is what we are going to do now So with the
following example um I kind of want to walk you
through um how you can write actually uh an object
uh inside of the file So we have our contact man
context manager We create a t file This time we
call it f Um we create a histogram similar to
what you did in the in the previous part of the
session um just has some but still actually an
empty histogram and we call it h and to write this
object h into the file we can call write object
um on the file with um where we specify the actual
object and then the name of the object So we say h
and age.get name because we already gave h a name
which is minist um and then we can call it and it
doesn't really output anything but we can check
actually that it's that it wrote it in bit So as
you see here the the the argument of the th1D is
the name of the histogram which Yan has already
explained is kind of the common pattern where you
g the name to the object and good to note here is
that this name is actually also what we use to
identify the objects in the file So even though
in our Python program we called it H If we want
to then read it back from file in a in a different
program um it's not called H it will be called my
histo Um so that's maybe a good thing to note Okay
So now we should have a file or we already saw
that we have a file called my file.root Um but we
want to check uh whether actually it contains the
objects uh that we just wrote And let's first just
try with bash Um I'm sure I hope that everyone's
familiar with the ls command And we can see indeed
that there is a file called my file.root It's
also larger than what we saw before Has more
bytes So there's something written to it Um which
is already a bit reassuring Um but now if we want
to actually check if it contains the histogram
we just created we also provide a special command
called uh root ls that will actually show you
the commands within a root file So if you have a
root file and you only know the file name but you
aren't really sure what's in there Um you can use
root ls to to inspect actually the contents of the
of the file So to see it in action Yeah exactly So
we call root ls with uh exactly the same command
uh -l with uh the file name and it shows you that
uh we have a th1D uh written on 14th of
June with a um histogram called my histo
and actually it also contains the type Now this
is all fine You have the file you know how to
show it in bash Um but of course you also want to
be able to interact with it Uh because you create
histogram you write it out but then you want to
uh fill it or maybe plot it or I don't know you
want to programmatically interact with it Um we
can do it again by using T file So now we open
uh again with the context manager we open the file
Notice that I don't give a don't give an argument
right now because I don't want to recreate I don't
want to update I just want to read um which will
be the default And then I can on the on the file
object I can call get um with again the name of
the histogram we just created So let's see what it
does exactly So now we open the file we get it and
um we can verify here that we have a histogram
called my histo which exactly what we created
So that's files in general Um now let's move a
bit into uh what's usually in these files which
are uh H data sets because I don't know what
what what your background is Um just to make
sure we're on the same page A high energy physics
data set uh typically contains many many um we're
talking about couple of million per profile of
uh statistically independent collision events
Maybe the the naive solution would be to create
an object with my event and then have multiple
of them uh and read them back Um however that is
very inefficient because every event has hundreds
to sometimes uh thousands of data fields and
if you need to write read back every data field
every time uh yeah you you might uh need a lot of
coffee breaks before your before your analysis is
finished Um so instead we thought about how we can
store this efficiently and um so we came up with a
data set um specification that it's columnar um
so a data set we organized in different columns
um and these columns can store elements of any
C++ type so it's fundamental types like integers
floats uh you can use collections so vectors maps
arrays or you can even provide your own classes
So if you have a class um my electron uh you
could write your yeah an object of my electron
uh into a data set and to kind of show you what
it looks like uh from a very very um high level
point of view Um so every the green part here is
is an event or an entry Um and then this entry is
split up into into columns or typically we also
refer to it as as branches and it can be anything
like a can be a number it can be an object um
and kind of a way to also think about this is
uh a high performance excel sheet so you have
really this tabular view on your data and this
data set we call it t tree or it's the name of
the of the class we uh we use it again so it's
a tree with the t in front of it Um and it
can be written to a T file just as any other
um C++ object or root object as we just saw Um and
the nice thing about this format is that you can
read columns independently which is very nice if
you have a massive data set of maybe a thousand
fields or branches or columns or whatever you want
to call it and you really only need two or three
It wouldn't make any sense to read everything
But with this way you can really um optimize
the IO so the reading and writing from disk uh
performance uh especially with with respect to
other data set formats that already exist Going to
show you what a T3 looks like We again used the so
now this example file already existed You can find
it in the repository as well If we call root ls on
this example file you'll see that we will have a
a t tree called data set and we can interact with
[Music]
this We now know that we have a t file with my
data set um and we want to be able to actually
analyze the data that's inside of it Um the
recommended way is um nowadays roots are
data frame and here is also where I kind of will
contradict what what J said in the beginning that
every root class is prepended with a t This is
actually not fully true because the modern classes
and and um interfaces we have will actually start
with an R which also logically maybe makes more
sense So if you have the choice between using an
R interface or a T interface I would recommend
using the interface that starts with an R because
it's the latest and greatest Okay So in our case
we are well now we're talking about uh roots our
data frame and it's really the high level analysis
interface So if you're doing physics analysis is
really what we recommend you to use It's very nice
to define the steps that you have to take for your
analysis uh the sequence of operations and then
under the hood our data frame takes care of making
sure that everything is optimized and runs as fast
as it uh can run So with root our data frame you
can provide different sources you can actually
you don't only need to read from from root files
it's the most common way but you can actually also
create an data frame from a CSV file or uh from a
numpy array which we'll see in a bit Um and then
you provide your steps So that could be a filter
it could be a definition of a new column Um it
could be anything And then you output it to a
histogram your new root files that you can use
then perform your fits or yeah really any any user
find user defined operation Just to summarize our
data frame really allows for writing and and
actually also uh sorry reading and actually
also writing uh trees And really our goal is to
make life easy for you So how it works in action
um as with the other root interfaces what you do
to open is you need the name of your tree or the
name of your data set in general and then the
path to uh this data set Uh this can be a path
to on your local machine It can also be a URL to
to a file that's hosted somewhere else And then
to create our data frame simply we call root dot
our dataf frame with the name of the data set and
the path to the data set And pretty much that's it
So to see it in action um again we have to import
root and we open it and yeah exactly So we open we
have the data frame and you can see that we have
four columns a b ve one and ve two which we now
can actually start using uh to define our analysis
Let's let's call it for now So we can define new
quantities which means with that um so we started
with four columns and using define actually add
more columns also using the data that's already
in the file we can filter rows according to
some conditions for example if you have the
column a you only want the val the the entries
for which the value of a is larger or or smaller
than a certain amount and we can do some data
aggregations So to see it in action for example in
the define we want an additional property called C
which is derived from the columns that we already
have A and B So we can call dataf frame.define
and uh really just give the expression on the
names of the columns So we don't know we don't
have to know exactly what's in the columns only
have to know that it's in numerical value Then we
can actually define a filter on this new property
C Um so we're only interested in the entries in
the data frame that have uh C smaller than uh than
a half We can count the number of of elements
that are left in our set We can get the mean
uh and then we uh display the values that we have
So see it in action So we can see that um after we
have performed our filter uh we're left with 111
uh events and the mean of our uh of our column
C is um 0.38 39 Um and we can actually show the
first n entries by default is five uh entries of
the data set just to quickly verify yeah what it
looks like And we can see that's actually correct
We did the addition right Okay So that's really
our data frame um in a nutshell Of course now you
also want to do uh or once you've uh executed your
analysis you've defined your your um well defined
your filters your calculations um you want to see
your results and uh of course Jonas already showed
how it works with uh with histograms and and with
functions But our data frame really also can help
you to streamline the creation of histograms and
graphs and um any way to to show your results So
for example and again we used JS root again it
looks very similar to to what you already saw
we have to create a canvas But now what we do
differently is we already have the data frame
and really only what we need to do if for example
we want to create a histogram showing the results
of the contents of ve one is call data frame
his 1D and then the name of the column we want
to create the histogram for then we can draw it
and and draw the canvas as usual uh we get a nice
histogram and even though um so as you might
already guess from the name V one is actually
not flat data but it's uh entries containing
uh vectors that maybe are different sizes for
every entry RDF really is able to to nicely like
merge it together into one one size data frame
uh without you having to think too much about it
but you can think about it if you want and just
to to kind of give an overview so histo 1D will
create a one-dimensional histogram so that the one
you already saw and then we also have functions
for two and three dimensional and it's as easy
as providing just only the column name but you can
also actually provide more parameters in the form
of a tupole that you can pass that you already
saw in uh in the let's call vanilla histogram
function so the number of bins min the max we can
give the histogram a name we can give it a title
we can say the number of bins uh the x low the x
up and then put it all in a pupil and give it to
the histo 1D function and then if we execute it
you'll actually see so it's the same data that we
saw in the previous histogram but now with these
parameters we actually can kind of control what
parts are visible in the histogram and I have some
points that are maybe good for you to to take home
really if you uh start using our data frame and
analysis in general So RDF is really built with
a with a flexible workflow in mind and the most
important part is that you think really about
how your data flows through the workflow So if you
have certain properties really the important thing
is to think about which parts do I need to filter
which parts do I need to define and yeah how does
it kind of look if I draw it out as a kind of like
a like a graph uh which hardly can also do for you
what really does it look like from a bird's eye
point of view and then of course you can also uh
once you have this data flow uh apply actions to
it so such as creating creating histogram a really
important note here is I mentioned mentioned
that under the hood our data frame does a lot of
optimizations and make sure that the the analysis
can be run as fast as possible There's one task
that's kind of left as a responsibility to you
to the user and that's to make sure that all the
transformations and and actions So creating
the filters creating the defines saying that
you would like to create a histogram It's really
important that you kind of write this down like
define this in your code before you do actually
anything with the results And the reason is that
our data frame u has this notion of laziness which
means that first we schedule what needs to happen
and then only if you want to access the results
the execution happens So if you already access
the results and then start amending to it kind of
the whole notion of this laziness is removed Um
so really only yeah try to be as lazy as possible
that would be um yeah and then really only after
that look at your results So we have our data set
and we want to create three histograms one for A
one for B one for ve one Now if you create
the histogram and then get the value from
the histogram or plot the histogram after each
definition of the histogram the data set will
get processed uh three times which is not ideal
because ideally you just want to process the data
set once and then only access the results So here
and the reason why it happened here is because you
call um this 1D then get value which will actually
run the workflow and then you do it again um twice
Now to do it correctly we would go the other way
We first define all our all of our histograms and
then only after that um mucle get value and the
you can see that the data set is only processed
once I just want to give a summary on the type
of operations that we have in in uh in RDF and
there are three main types of of operations So the
first one is transformations and that's really the
category of uh filters defines and there's also
one called alias which really lets you define
or the thing what it does is it lets you kind of
rename certain columns and there's there's a bunch
more that you can find in the in the documentation
So it really modifies the actual data frame
uh that you're using for your processing Then
the second one is actions which you can use to
aggregate parts or maybe even the entire data set
into a result So for example creating a histogram
or counting the number of events processed uh
getting the mean getting the min getting the max
And then we have a third one um which is queries
which are actually not being put into the workflow
um they are really kind of to for you to get
information about your data frame For example
what are the names of the columns I have in the
data set yeah What are the types you can actually
and and then save graphs If you have your nice
workflow you can actually create a visualization
of what it looks like just for you to visually
verify that all the filters are in the right
place And um yeah just [Music] check your task or
your Yeah Your challenge your exercise is to find
the hidden uh normal distribution So really what
you have to do is use our data frame to define
the filters find the defines and then find uh yeah
the the hidden distribution by uh by the natural
logarithm Um there are two links The first one is
the our dataf frame class reference and it really
shows you the the name of the functions and
the type of um actually show you it will show
you exactly all the functions you can call It
has a really nice uh cheat sheet that's divided
according to the the three categories that um I
explained earlier So we have the transformations
the actions and then the the queries And this
is really a perfect like starting point for for
using RDF If you want to do something but aren't
really sure what it's called you can just go here
say for example you need to define a filter can
click on here and it will bring you to actually
the interface uh and it will tell you exactly
what the arguments are uh you need One thing to
note is that this is the um documentation is for
C++ but you can pretty much one-on-one also use
it for for Python Um and then second one has some
uh tutorials uh both in C++ and Python and you can
use it as an example and maybe see if you can mix
and match some of the things for your uh solution
The first step that's that we need to do is to
create the data set which we know how to do with
the data set name that we were told and the root
file And the second step which we can actually
do in just one line consists of a few substeps
So I'm pretty sure that most of you got to the
filtering part So that the b has to be less
than or less or equal than 0.5 And then the
second part that was maybe slightly more tricky
is to define this logarithm of a And here we're
using the the root tmath class which gives you
the log a So this is the second step And then
uh we were told that if we look into the
distribution of this new column that we called log
a we should get the normal distribution And now we
can just use the JS root command Now we can just
um do the drawing So the root t canvas and
we draw the histograms and then we draw the
canvas and what we obtain is indeed something
that that looks like the normal distribution
[Music] We are going to discuss now
um something which is very very common
um for for high energy physical analysts uh which
is the fact that we have to most often work with
the collections in our data sets So you will have
since the data sets often represent uh physical
quantities of particles that collided in an event
or that resulted as a collision um you will have
more than one element in the same in the same
row So that that is why you have collections Um
in our data frame you have certain specificities
For example you will you will see here and there
um something that is called root arc uh popping
up This is just the in-memory representation of
a vector a vector of uh particle properties
uh that we have in root So nothing nothing
um weird about it It's just our own way of
representing it But you can just visualize
it as a as a vector in mind And um other than
that now we will take a look at the first at
the first example here Let me zoom out and then
we start So we have our usual um constructor for
the R data frame object This time if this is still
visible I hope this time we have a different data
set a different file And in this data set we have
four columns um with the with the following names
that you can see here And now we would like to to
inspect the data set uh and in particular here I
will use um a functionality available in our data
frame which is already a bit more advanced which
is the possibility to convert one or more more
columns of your data set into numpy arrays and in
this case let me just start with one column the
column uh e um if you if you call these s numpy
uh object method here uh you will get a dictionary
of numpy arrays where the key is the name of the
column and the value is the numpy array
representing the the values in the column
and I'm simply in this cell I am printing uh one
by one all the elements of this particular column
row per row so in every row we have three uh in
particular row zero row one and row two I wanted
to print it out explicitly to screen to show you
the fact that they not only we have collections
inside of the column uh but we also have um that
every row has a different size of the collection
and u and you have to keep this in mind because it
makes uh things a bit harder to to manipulate and
process right in your uh in your data analysis
pipelines So now comes really the important bit
um of this um of this part of the lecture and and
I will take some time to discuss what's happening
here Here we are for the first time trying to do
something to process somehow the the data set that
contains collections and we want to perform an
operation that has both the the aspect of creating
a new observable but at the same time we are also
performing a selection Let's take it step by step
In the expression that you can see highlighted
in the middle of the of the slide there are three
variables three observables px py and e These
are the columns of our data set And then we are
doing some manipulation here From left to right we
have an external call to a square root operation
with an argument And then right after the square
root operation we have this brackets with square
brackets um syntax Now the the square bracket
syntax is exactly the same as a as a numpy square
bracket syntax What we are doing here is we are we
are um masking the outer array with the elements
from the condition the criterion present within
the square brackets So let's take a look at that
for a second We have E greater than 100 You can
guess what this does It checks for every value of
the numpy array of the array at the current event
of the column E whether that value is greater or
not than 100 So the output of E greater than 100
is not just one boolean like one true or false
It's it's a collection of booleans one per
each element from the from the array E Right
and this is how then the outer array So the
result of the square root will be masked So
whatever comes out of the square root operation on
the left will be another array But then we select
from that array only the elements that pass the
selection criterion E greater than greater than
100 And okay so now we can then go to the square
root operations In particular the parameters here
as I said before they are collections So we are
in in the current event we have px and py they
represent the collections of px and py for the
particles in the event and you see that we are
performing some manipulations here we are uh
multiplying them we are summing them and then
there's their square root the important bit
to remember here is that the dimensionality
of the arrays is always preserved uh what do I
mean by this px * px is a scalar product between
the two between the two vectors so you will have
the same dimension coming out of the operation
The sum is again preserving the dimensionality
So if px and p y have size three then the sum of
them will be still a size three vector with the
elements uh summed element by element And then
the square root same thing So in general we are
preserving the dimensionality of the input arrays
Um and then finally the whole expression
is give me the square root of the of the
um uh square of the sum of squares of the two
vectors and then select only the elements that
um pass the criterion I said that we are doing
a selection right because there's this masking
operation with the array greater than 100 So
when I say selection it kind of in you could
think about it as as filtering your data as cut
as a cut in your your analysis workflow But there
is an important distinction here The distinction
is between interevent selection and intraevent
selection So the first category is whenever you
have a question a query which output should be
true or false So for example give me all the
events where the number of muons is greater
than two Uh for every event you check how many
muons do I have is it greater than two or not
and this if it's false it means that you do not
want to see that event at all for the rest of your
analysis You don't care about it So you discard it
Operations that discard an entire event these are
proper properly called filters or cuts And in our
data frame you use the filter operation that we
have seen before for this type of um of filtering
In this case we are doing a filter but we are not
logically discarding the entire event We are we
are saying okay within this event I want to keep
some of the particles those that respect respect
a certain criterion So in this case we are still
interested in seeing the event afterwards just
slightly modified So this is why in this example
you see the define operation being called and
not the filter operation This is an important
distinction and kind of the main point when
processing uh array data with with our data
frame Okay So the question is um here in this
particular example we are using the square root
function and why don't we need to prefix any
name space to the square root function Well in
this case the square root function comes from the
standard C++ name space So this is stood square
uh square root The way the the C++ programming
language works is if the function arguments in
this case px py these are these are of type
arebec If the function arguments match with
the signature of the square root function that
has that type so root artbec then um the the the
compiler the program will execute the correct
function even without you having to explicitly
write the the name space and in this case it's
not ambiguous because there is not another uh
square root function at the global namespace
let's say so the the compiler knows what to do
um and this in particular is also different
from the t-math colon square root function So
um there's no ambiguity there You could use
of course Yeah Here instead you can you can
give tmath square root or you can define
your own square root function and use that
The only the only requirement is that it can be
interpreted by our C++ interpreter Yes for now at
least Now we have this new column good PT and we
can try to plot it with the usual 1D operations
that we have seen already many times now
and it should be visible here Yes So now
we have this histogram that is being um that is
being plot uh only keeping the elements the the
values of the PT of each event that passed
the selection process in the previous slide
It's going to be an exercise on on the same on
the same subject So we have um the data set that
we used in the previous exercise and we know that
this data set contains two vector um columns back
one and ve two Um we have a mixture of gshian
and some background noise in the ve one column
And then there is an assignment to remove this
noise in order to plot the gshian peaks Uh in in
order to do that you can se select the elements of
vec one the column ve for which the square of the
corresponding elements in vec 2 is less than 0.1
So the exercise is to um do perform this selection
process in order to then plot the histogram of ve
one that shows this uh um the two the two gshian
peaks So again the assignment was to uh find the
peaks of gshians that were hidden in this uh in
this data set Let's uh quickly open our data frame
object So we have the data set from uh example
style.root Um and then we have we're interested
in columns ve one and ve two We have to do this
task of removing the background noise by
selecting the elements of ve one for which
the square of the corresponding elements
in ve two is less than 0.1 So we have this
uh objective of doing a selection intraevent
within the same event event by event clearly
So we we have to create a new column in
this case uh it's going to be uh good
uh good particles and here what we do is we
call define um with the name of this column
and what is the what is the selection that
we have to perform So we want the elements
of vect one in the end So vector one is going to
be our output vector and then we can do the the
square bracket selection like like with with a
numpy array And in this case these the selection
criteria is the criterion is the square uh of the
corresponding elements in back two is less than uh
0.1 So so you see even though we
are performing a selection it is
indeed a case where we want to create
a new column just to store the values
uh that of the of the correct particles that uh
pass the selection And then we can um use our
good old trusty uh 1D operation on this new on
this new column And then we do the plotting So
canvas and then see the draw Let's
see if everything went according to
plan Something didn't went
go according to plan Data
Sorry Ah data Yes Good
So okay we open the data set we create this
selection and then we see the histogram being
plot So you have the two picss You could have
also decided to plot back one just to check
And if we do that see that there was this
extra noise in the original column that we
removed by by creating the good particles all
did Was anybody successful in in this exercise
just as a show of raise of ants okay Okay It's
one of the more advanced concepts here in the
data set manipulation step So uh try try
to take some time really to make it yours
[Music] How to save a data set once you are done
processing it You remember from the slides that
Florina was discussing that we have this concept
of the root file So the T file and that we can
store anything in it and this includes also root
data sets which come in this format that is known
as T3 Um it turns out that our data frame is
your best friend when you just want to save
stuff when you want to save T3 into a file because
there's one simple function that you can call It's
called snapshot and it will store a T3 properly
formatted into a T file given the uh parameters
that you pass to the function So you can see it in
this example here at the end of the at the end of
the cell The parameters are self-explanatory You
have a you have the name of the tree the name of
the data set that you want to store the name of
the file that you want to store the data set in
and then you can also make a selection of columns
In in fact in this example we are taking the the
usual file from our data directory We are creating
a new column called C and then we are saving it
together with columns A and B So you see that we
have this list of columns and then you can pass
the list of columns as the third argument And if
we if we execute it okay we will see in the next
cell that there is an actual file on disk with the
correct name and that it contains the um the T3
that we expected with the columns that we expected
So in particular you see that this file has a T3
object that its name is out three the same name
as we uh as we chose and then there are there's
a list of columns uh stored inside of the tree A
B and C If you go back uh to the previous example
here and you just also write back one from the
from the from the name of the columns of before
even a better example than this is showing you
the fact that by default this snapshot operation
doesn't need this list of column names and if
you do not provide the list of column names it
will just store all the columns that are available
to the data frame up to that point So I can just
repeat this cell and then go here and then if I
rerun the cell now it will show all the columns
A C B A ve 2 and ve one So all of the columns
that were available before they're they're now
available in the in the tree because by default
that's what the snapshot does And finally we have
maybe you have not noticed it uh automatically
but this snapshot operation does not only store
on disk but also returns something So there's a
there's a return variable up here and the return
variable can actually be used again and it's just
another R data frame object So you can for example
display its contents because it's available uh in
memory in memory of the computer as another R data
frame object kind of detached from the previous
one So you can restart your analysis and do other
kinds of operations and manipulations
with this Um some other topic is about
uh again about the selection processes This uh is
this is a recurrent theme in physics of course and
the concept of cut flow reports So sometimes you
want to um get a nice uh representation of how
your filters affect the the data set that you're
manipulating So the filter efficiency depending on
uh the the columns the branches and which particle
properties you're observing with the selections
in our data frame you have this report operation
that gathers all the information from the filter
uh calls that you have uh applied to your data set
and then prints out this report if you ask it to
uh after the uh event loop after the computation
has run So in this case I am taking a new file
Uh note as a just something that is uh good
to know that this file doesn't even belong
to the local disk the local file system but I am
actually passing it as a URL This is very typical
in our field We have large data sets and they
are very very frequently stored um outside of
your laptop outside of your of your machine that
you're running on So we have the ability to read
them from the remote location that they're stored
at And here I'm opening an R data frame reading
data from this particular file I have two filters
on on leptton properties and I give them names
So a cut on the cut on the fi and then the report
operation down here at the bottom will tell me how
many events passed the filter how many events were
present before the filter uh and then just as a
summary report the efficiency of every filter and
the commutative efficiency of all the filters so
far
Okay All right Clearly we have already seen in
previous uh in previous notebooks that root is
this package that lets you use Python and C++
together our data frame is no difference there
Um and uh the way that you've seen for example
Yonas in the beginning reporting on how you can
use C++ libraries define your custom functions
and use them from the Python side is the same in
our data frame Uh under the hood it calls this
uh C++ interpreter which is called cling uh to
use to use the C++ functions that you've defined
This function is a very simple one that takes a
number and changes its type uh in this case and
uh I'm calling it sloat So it's a function that
does a cast in the end And then we can okay this
is another function that squares a floating point
value And now you we can use the functions in our
data frame quite simply You can either use them
with this uh string syntax as we have seen so far
You can also use them with the other syntax that
we showed before that they become part of the
root module So you have root dot function that
you just defined Um and uh and this is how it's
uh working in action So after the definition of
the um of the new values of the new columns we
can just plot them for example in a graph and
uh and the graph will be shown using the values
from the data frame So this is all um bread and
butter stuff for area frame analysis You will
mostly see this in some frameworks uh that are
already available in some uh in some experiment
groups Um and they use the libraries and the
functions that that are defined in the framework
itself Often they're also defined in C++ They use
them in our data frame in this way even if the
user side of the framework is written in Python
And finally as a as a final mention uh our data
frame and clearly root in general is a very
performanceoriented software in particular all the
nice uh features of lazy execution and uh booking
all your your operations up front that we were
discussing earlier they come in handy especially
when you want to um introduce parallelism in your
application So nowadays every laptop has at least
four cores practically um or at least four threads
but uh most often you will see machines with uh
upwards of hundreds of cores and uh and clearly
it's very nice if you could actually make use of
of those resources and our data frame lets you do
this quite simply um you just have to write one
line of code at the beginning of your application
the line of code is as follows um okay in this
case I'm Just showing you the baseline example
by uh taking yet another file opening an R data
frame with it and then summing the values of
one column takes some time And then in the
next cell I will do the same but pay attention
to this first line You call root enable implicit
MT and then everything else will run using the
maximum amount of cores available on the machine
uh I will run the cell now It's quite probable
that it will run as slow or even slower than the
previous cell for a simple reason The reason is
that this is not a powerful machine but it's a
shared instance with just two cores and the data
set is a data set stored remotely So it's not a
performanceoriented scenario here But if you might
happen to have a performanceoriented scenario and
you have a powerful machine at hand then just
know that with one line of code you go from
using one core to 128 cores on your machine So it
could be quite useful to to keep in [Music] mind
This is this is a simple very simple example of
an analysis um with open data from CMS and the
goal of the analysis is to plot the invariant
mass of the dimeu system So for the physicists
in the audience you know what we are about to do
Um and let's see let's try to do this together
right um let me kickstart the notebook for you or
with you and then um then I will let you attempt
u writing the the important bits of the analysis
So the data set in question as I said is an open
data file from from CMS stored on a remote
location in the certain data center In this
table we are just showing the um columns
and the data types that you have inside of
the data set Right so there are six columns
Uh most of them are vectors are collections
and only one represents the number of muons in
in the particular event that you're processing
first cell is easy We are just giving you the
name of the tree and the name of the file or the
path to the remote file so that our data frame can
process it Um and then and then the rest is where
the analysis really really is Um the first cell
here is is just a detail This analysis has this
data set has 61 million events uh probably there
would be they would be too many if we try to run
them right now altogether It would take a bit of
time So I'm doing this I'm just showing you how to
select with our data frame the first one million
events You have this simple um df.trange operation
So write it in that notebook cell and then our
data frame will only process the first one million
events from the data set so that you can see the
results bit quicker It will the the the final
histogram maybe will not be as clear as this There
will be less statistics but it will still show you
uh roughly the same roughly the same distribution
Okay And then we have two parts of the analysis
One is the filtering of the events that are you
know interesting for uh getting the invariant
mass and the other one is creating the invariant
mass In this case because there is already a very
simple function ready made for you and available
in in root we we just wrote it already for you So
you don't have to care about that But the filters
are there for you to fill in So you have to you
have to understand what to write in the cuts or
you you can think about it and then um and then
you can plot the histogram afterwards There's also
requests for booking a report of the operations So
it would be nice if you didn't only see the final
histogram but also the efficiencies of the of the
different cuts H let's take five minutes and then
let's do this together afterwards We stopped at
this cell right uh we are just selecting the first
million events so that uh whenever we try to plot
the histogram actually it won't be too won't
take too long Okay And this this was the next
cell So the text above the cell tells you already
uh the kind of selection criteria that you want to
apply And then there are two two filters um that
have already in in them the the hint as to what
you have to do The part that is missing is the
expression So for the expression the first filter
is the one where the events should have exactly
two muons How do we write the expression here yes
All right And mu1 equal equal 2 This makes sense
right because if we go to back to this table that
shows the that the data set schema we know that
the n muon column is the column that represents
the number of muons in the particular event So
for every event if we check whether nuon is equal
equal to then we know that we have exactly two
muons Okay Next uh next filter next selection
charge equal equal to zero M charge equal equals
Z This is what you wrote or ju just to make sure
I I'm understanding Yeah Yeah Okay So muon charge
equal equals 0 Let's try to think about this We
go back to the table and we see that muon charge
is um an an array of type int The dimension of
the array is n mu1 Mhm And it says charge of the
muon stored as an array of size and muon either
minus one or one Clearly this is the charge
Okay If we go back to the selection here what
we are doing is tell me if the array is equal
equals zero But from from the perspective of
the array we don't know whether what will this
operation do will it do every every element is
equal to zero or are you expecting this to do
that to do something like tell me if the size
of the array is equal to zero What what's your
expected outcome from the operation so the the
thing that the assignment says here is that the
muons in this event should have opposite charge
So what I am missing from this selection
here is something that tells me that two
elements of the array should be should be
opposite No because we we are looking for
the muons that have opposite charge Did anybody
try anything else maybe down there Yes Okay So
the sum over the elements of the array clearly
How what does this mean let's try to look at it
We have an array and we know that the array is
size two because the filter that we did before is
only give me those events that have two muons So
the muon charge will be an array of size two Okay
we know that the array is an array of integers
and it's either minus1 or one Interesting So
if we sum two elements and they are and the sum
is zero then we derive that minus1 + 1 is zero
Okay this is an interesting approach How did you
write this with a for loop with some operation
to accumulate okay Okay Okay Okay So what we could
do is writing it um this way So we could do in sum
right and we can do for um auto zero a less than
new charge dot size plus uh we do sum plus equal
uh mu1 charge of type uh sorry of index I and
then we return sum equal equal zero This is
uh roughly speaking the implementation of what
you described So we sum the elements of the array
into an external variable and then what we return
which is the important part Maybe let's write this
like so If we write come on okay if we write
it this way it will be a bit clearer probably
So we have the for loop and then what we return
is the important part right we we have a return
statement and we say in the return statement
tell me whether the sum is equal to zero Okay
interesting Were there any other attempts at
this okay So this could be a second approach We
have it here Uh we could do mu1 charge of zero the
first element is equals to minus - -1 * new charge
of index one Mhm Okay Yes This is also another
approach Let's try I don't know is there a third
way let's try with the first just for the sake
of going on with the exercise Good Um okay This
is the other part of the analysis but in this
case root already offers a nice invariant mass
function So you don't have to um code it yourself
So there was nothing to do here And this is the
final bit where we are creating the histogram
And the exercise was asking you to put the uh
the histogram parameters in the right order This
is just to check to see if after a couple of hours
seeing histograms over and over you remember the
the order of the parameters What's the first one
right Okay So name title and bins and
then the range of the of the x-axis
Okay then the request for booking a report
should be simple What do we write here we
saw this in the notebook just before the
exercise Maybe I went a bit too fast on
it So the the title kind of tells
you right the title of the slide
There's this functionality in RDF which we
will see used here exactly called report
Um so whenever you want to know how your filters
were applied to the data set you can ask to the
dataf frame object What did I do here um right
You can ask to the data frame object to report
um what happened during the filters So was just
a simple simple check here Okay we booked it and
finally we can actually start the analysis right
um there is some customization of the layout of
the histogram done for you so that when when you
go and match it with the link that we provided it
kind of looks the same So let's start let's start
the cell and let's see if everything runs without
problems Okay nice So everything seems to run
without problems Final check Let's see how the
histogram looks Okay pretty cool No it's uh shows
the same distribution as the open data as the open
data result Clearly if you go look at the other
picture you will see it bit more defined whereas
uh here it's a bit wiggly but clearly that's
because we only restricted ourselves to the
first million events And then just to end the
exercise you can ask the report to print the
values obtained from the two filters So
you have the first filter on the events
uh that have two muons From 1 million we go
uh down to almost 500,000 And then the second
filter where we check the muons with opposite
charge we go from from that number to 371,000
And that's what you actually see in the in the
output from uh this cell So today we covered
a number of topics We had a nice introduction
into uh what ROOT allows you to do specifically
uh everything that has to deal with the parts
of the workflow that are more related with
the analysis So um creating histograms important
statistics from your data set how to run fitting
uh on your on your statistics creating a file
opening a file writing stuff into the file and
then finally uh a big expression into uh our data
frame analysis um and and how it can actually be
practically useful if you have ROOT files and
you want to uh process them Uh in this other
slide we leave you the usual list of resources
Feel free to reach out to us uh in any way or
shape You can see we have a forum we have uh
websites and documentation and you can find
us uh if you have any problems also on GitHub
uh you can open uh issues Cool Uh the rest of
the uh of the slides is just extra material for
for you for self-study in case you uh you would
like to go a bit deeper into ROOT. And with that
said uh thanks again for joining us today from
me and the rest of the team and um yeah have
a nice rest of your summer studentship at CERN